I'm just taking the back end of your uh
published bio talking about fellow of
the Royal Society biology
2012 uh Welden Memorial prize
2013 uh embo um uh Excellence priz 2014
Academia Europa
2015 thankfully you haven't updated
since
uh on 2016 Charles brnch award for for
on on parallel contribution brain
research and the glass brain award uh
really glad to have you Among Us um and
thank you over to you for the physics of
sentience thank you very much for that
wonderful introduction and your kind
comments uh it's a great pleasure to be
here and it does feel like a very warm
Community um I'm going to share my
screen and then
hopefully that will set us all up
so let me repeat my um my thanks uh for
being here I'm going to start with um as
usual with this talk an apology but a
very specific apology now I don't have a
foundational training in cybernetics um
but I have over the course of the work
um largely inspired by Neuroscience but
appealing to physics during my career it
has become very clear that cybernetics
um and the kind of work that I've been
engaged with have very intimate
relationships and probably share certain
foundations along with things like
perceptual control theory so um but I
repeat I do not have a foundational
training um in these disciplines so what
I've got to offer in the first hour of
this session um is really a view of
self-organization and sentient behavior
from through the lens of a physicist and
neuroscientist in the fond hope that you
will be able to join the dots and see
how it can be translated in terms of uh
your the the basic principles which with
which you will be much more familiar um
so I'm going to divide the talk into uh
three parts first of all um telling a
story about Behavior about um
self-organization from the point of view
of statistical physics and information
Theory um with a special focus on markof
blankets and how markof blankets
individuate things that possess
attributes such as behavior um and
trying to understand those attributes in
terms of something that we refer to as a
Bas in mechanics um and then I'm going
to tell the exactly the same story but
using the concepts and the constructs
that come from neuroscience science of
neurobiology so how would these um
physics like principles be applied to
the brain uh to things like you and me
um or indeed single cells uh and I'm
going to illustrate that in terms of
predictive coding and neuronal networks
as a particular instance or application
of the physics that we're going to cover
in the first part and then if we have
time um I'd like to just um drill down
on the nature of agency within this kind
of treatment um and specifically um talk
about the difference between mere
reflexive behaviors of the kind you
might say find in a in a
thermostat um and the sort of planning
um and deliberate behavior and agency
that we find in things like uh things
like ourselves um and I would you know
I'm looking forward to a conversation
about whether that bright line is
necessary and how it does relate to um
um cybernetics I'm going to start with
um a question posed by scoder how can
the events in space and time which take
place within the spatial boundary of a
living organism be accounted for by
physics and
chemistry I'm not going to answer that
question and clearly we can't do that um
but what we can do is just um highlight
the notion of a spatial boundary as
being requisite to be able to talk about
anything in the sense that to talk about
some
entity some particle some person or
something you need to be able to
individuate it from everything else in
the universe so I'm going to read that
thing as a statistical object or the
boundary that defines is definitive of
that thing as a statistical boundary um
specifically a markof blanket um so for
those of you who are not familiar with
the mark of blanket um notion it's a
very ubiquitous construct in uh
statistics SS and in causal inference um
but plays a foundational role in what
I'm about to say I repeat simply because
it is the device that allows you to
separate or individuate um the internal
States and the blanket states of
something from everything else so more
specifically I've just tried to cartoon
the intuition here in terms of a very
simple little Universe where these blue
circles represent some abstract state of
the universe and the arrows denote an
influence of one state on another state
and if I were to pick um a particular
set of states and to say my
States and we'll call my these states
internal States or states that are
internal to me the mark of blanket is
defined in terms of the parents the
children and the parents of the children
of the internal States and the role of
the Markoff blanket is to provide a kind
of
insulation a kind of separation between
the internal States and the remaining
States the external States here so
technically what this means is that if I
wanted to predict the Dynamics or
evolution of my internal States given
the rest of the Universe I would only
need to know the markof blanket all the
information about the entire universe
that is pertinent to me to my internal
States is contained upon this boundary
or these Mark or this Markoff blanket um
mathematically that just means that the
internal states are conditionally
independent of the external States given
the blanket States so that's my
definition of thingness um uh and I'm
going to make a further move here I'm
going to um make a bipartition of the
blanket States into sensory States and
active States U according to the very
simple rule that the
um the sensory States influence but are
not influenced by the internal States
and similarly the active States
influence but are not influenced by the
external States um so I've now
effectively got a partition of all the
states in the universe or this
particular little Universe um that
enables me to identify a particle or
some entity that comprises the internal
States and the blanket states that
themselves can be divided into active
and sensory States and you may be asking
why have I done this well it it
organizes a way of thinking about all
the kinds of systems that we um as
scientists and philosophers like to
think about two of my favorite systems
are here uh the brain um so under this
kind of partition defined by these
sparse couplings um the arrows how can
we cons consider the brain well the
brain would have internal States all my
um you synaptic activities my
connectivity everything I need to list
in order to define the state of the
brain at this point in time and the
internal states are going to influence
the active States they my actuators my
autonomic reflexes um that perform
actions on the external states that then
change my sensory epithelium my sensory
states that are uh then going to
influence my internal brain States and
so the cycle begins and exactly the same
causal dependency structure or
separation or partition of States can be
found um any way you look so for example
a single cell will have intracellular
internal states that are internal to say
the actin filaments of a cell uh that
are themselves beneath the sensory
states that are pushed out into the
external states that reciprocate in
terms of causal influences uh by
activating cell surface receptors that
change the intracellular states that uh
change the action and so forth on both
uh both of these
examples you have this notion that the
inside is influencing the outside
vicariously through the active States
while the outside is influencing the
inside again vicariously through the
sensory states and this sort of
completes a a a circular causality that
as a neuroscientist one could read as
your a very elementary form of an action
perception cycle um what I'm going to do
now though is just to ask you to forget
about the markof blanket we're going to
now rehearse 101 physics um to the
extent that we need to to pursue the
argument having established the core
physics uh at hand with going to put the
mark of blanket back into play and see
what special properties emerge um and
I'm framing it like that because the
starting point for this is exactly the
same starting point that you would find
in all kinds of mechanics whether it's
quantum mechanics statistical mechanics
or classical mechanics it starts really
with uh an expression of the Dynamics of
some universe and I've sketched that out
here in terms of uh in this instance a
lan equation so the rate of change of
some states is just a function of the
state um plus some random fluctuations
Omega and I've cartooned that here um in
terms of two states um uh and this can
be read at many many different scales uh
for example it could be neuronal
oscillations um in one cell of my brain
as they course their trajectory of these
two states this two states State space
space over very f
um time scales say appropriate for gamma
oscillations uh it could be um my
cardiac cycle going through the phases
of the cardiac cycle it could be me
getting up in the morning um having a
cup of coffee doing my emails and
working through the day could be an
annual
cycle the point being here we are
interested in describing systems that
have a particular characteristic in fact
one could say um definitional uh
definitional of them um being uh
existing in the sense that they possess
characteristic States um the
characteristic in question is that they
always the system always revisits States
it was once in um and this could be read
in many ways it could be read as
possessing an attracting set or an
attracting manifold on which the states
evolve um it can be read as the solution
to a non-e equilibrium steady state um
and it can also be read um effectively
instead of being tracing out particular
trajectories we can read the density of
these trajectories as a probability that
you will find me in a particular state
if you sampled me at random and that's
the if you like the interpretation that
I'm going to pursue so why I focusing on
that interpretation well we know a lot
about the Dynamics not of the states in
and of themselves but of the dens
distribution the probability
distribution over um those States and um
some of you may or may not be familiar
with various expressions of the density
Dynamics I WR it down here in terms of a
poer plank equation so now it's a rate
of change not of the states but of the
probability density over the states that
is expressed here in terms of the
amplitude of the random
fluctuations and the flow um
and this equation is again ubiquitous in
physics and you know you could read it
as a continuous form of Master equation
it could be the time independent scrutin
equation wherever you look it's a
fundamental equation that describes
deterministically the evolution of the
probability distribution but I've just
said we're interested in describing
systems that have a characteristic set
of states such that this probability
distribution doesn't change with time
and that's the key move here so I'm
basically looking for
solutions
for these density dynamics that are now
characteristic of the Dynamics of
systems of interest that possess an
attracting set um and just by setting
this to zero and rearranging it um
specifically using in this instance the
hels decomposition what I can do is
Express the Dynamics the flow the way
that I change my States over time purely
as a function of the amplitude of these
random
fluctuations and the gradients of these
probabilities um strictly speaking the
log probabilities so and there's also
another term here known as a solenoidal
component so this is this is the
equation I want to focus on um because
it's got some really intriguing
interpretations um before I sort of get
into those interpretations uh maybe a
good idea to to explain why there are
two terms here um describing these flows
on these probability or log probability
gradients um one U this decomposition
basically is just describing the fact
that you can always split the flow into
two orthogonal components um the first
one um say for example we think about
water flowing down a bath um the plug
hole in a bath
um then the gradient flow is Flowing
down the gradients whereas the
solenoidal flow DED by Q here circulates
on the iso probability Contours or um
solenoidal shows this kind of solenoidal
effect as it circulates around so it's
just a way of breaking up the Dynamics
into a gradient
flow um on the one hand and some
circular flow on the other hand um both
of those have interesting implications
um you know the gradient flow we're
talking about is actually flowing if you
like up log probability gradients it's
like Gathering flowing up a
concentration of the probability of
finding in a particular State as if the
system was trying to gather itself into
its uh attracting set and resisting the
dispersive effect of the random
fluctuations the circular flow is
interesting as well because it it says
that the these kinds of systems must
have a form of oscillation or cyclical
aspect solenoidal aspect to them and of
course if you think about biological
systems they're full of biorhythms and
oscillations and indeed you could almost
say life cycles themselves are an
articulation or an expression of this
kind of um um ubiquitous kind of of
Dynamics so that's where we've arrived
the solution to the density Dynamics has
to have this functional form which can
be expressed as a gradient flow on these
log
probabilities excuse me what we'll do
now is uh bring the markof blankets back
and see if there is another kind of
mechanics that complements or U fits in
um the classical or
um statistical and and quantum mechanics
that can be derived from these uh
density
Dynamics so that flow
equation holds for all the states and
the particular petition that we
discussed um under the Markoff blanket
so the internal States will be doing uh
a gradient flow on the probability here
of the uh the mark of blanket States uh
as will the active States and notice by
construction I can drop the external
States because the internal States and
the active states are not influenced by
construction by the external States so
this leads to a slightly simpler form of
this um these gradient flows um that I'm
going to read in terms of perception and
action both in the service or look as if
they're in the service of maximizing the
log probability um of States so what are
the the
interpretations of this quantity this
log probability of some sensory States
given a Markoff blanket or given uh
given given me um and I've um listed a
few interpretations here um just to
illustrate um the again the importance
of this of this uh fundamental kind of
Dynamics this gradient flow if you
recall this probability
scores the likelihood you will find me
in these states there are states that
part of my attracting set they are
literally those states that attract me
and in that sense there are states that
are valuable for me given my Markoff
blanket um and all of these all that's
that this equation is saying is it looks
as if my internal States and the way I
act upon my world or my external states
are trying to maximize by flowing uphill
um this quantity which can be read now
as reinforcement learning if you're a
control theorist it would be optimal
control theory if you're an economist
could read this in terms of expected
utility Theory and that's nice because
the negative um of this uh value um if
you're an information theorist will be
known as the self-information uh the
implausibility of this sensory
observation or outcome or event given me
um more simply surprisal or even more
simply just a surprise um and from this
we can um spin out uh the principle of
Maximum Mutual information or the infax
principle equivalently the minimum
redundancy principle and indeed the free
energy principle um why the free energy
principle well the free energy is just a
bound uh or proxy for this uh this
surprise and I'll unpack the functional
form of this later on again trying to
give it give an intuition as to how one
can interpret the components of uh the
free energy equipping it with a you know
a teeology or a functional
interpretation which may or may not be
necessary to simulate um the behaviors
of of of
Interest the average of self-information
or surprise is just the entropy um which
means that this um fundamental gradient
flow will look as if it's trying to
minimize the dispersional the entropy of
the B the blanket States in this example
the sensory States and of course that's
just an expression of the Holy Grail um
um physics uh or the physics of self
organization um as articulated Say by
Herman hen's synergetics and if I was a
physiologist it would just be a
statement of homeostasis it would just
be a statement that systems that persist
in a physiological sense um are those
that show a generalized homeostasis they
are keeping their essential variables as
it were within viable bounds that are
characteristic of the physiology or the
the kind of thing uh that this system is
there's a final interpretation that I
want to pursue here which is the
interpretation that a statistician would
bring to the table um so if a
statistician saw this expression she
would think ah you are now writing down
the probability of some sensory
observation some data some sample uh
from the world or generated by some uh
process or world uh given not me on my
markof blanket but me considered as a
model of um the way in which my sensory
observations were generated and this
would be known in statistics as um um
the model evidence um also known as the
marginal likelihood um of these sensory
data and I emphasize the model of course
because what we're saying here is that
um to be uh to solicit valuable outcomes
and to minimize my surprise and to
self-organize in a way that resists the
second law if Second Law applied to open
systems of this sort is just to be a
good model of um my world and of course
this is just uh a statement of the good
regulator theorem from Ross Ashby and
colleagues uh but I'm going to pursue
exactly the same notion from the point
of view of statistician um leading to
things like the B Bas in brain
hypothesis um um also formulated in
terms of evidence accumulation Gathering
evidence for my model of the world um
and predictive coding which is the
example that I'll show later on that
leads to a specific process Theory um
that many people in the neurosciences uh
subscribe to In terms trying to
understand the Dynamics um of a brain
doing its sens making and Prosecuting uh
its actions upon the world so that's the
um that's the physics part um and now
we're going to tell the same story from
the point of view as if I was lecturing
to um people in Psychology or cognitive
Neuroscience um but it's the same it's
exactly the same same same ideas um I
think um nicely illustrated by this um
uh 16th century oil painter famed for
painting still lives that when viewed
from a different perspective give you
very different visual impression so if
previously you saw a bowl of fruit and
now you see a face the point he's making
here is that you made that face this is
a very active construction an
interpretation a hypothesis an
explanation a fantasy that you have used
to explain this particular of uh set of
Impressions on the sensory sector of
your marov blanket um so just to unpack
that a little bit more it really speaks
to the brain literally as a purveyor of
fantasies or literally a fantastic organ
that is evincing very much an inside out
kind of um um perspective on perception
which somewhat con contrasts with early
20th century view of a sort of um
outside in where the brain was um so
particularly say visual High hierarchies
were thought to extract information uh
from um the sensory input this turns
that on its head will have done then it
strange inversions and say no no um it
it feels it is a it is a um
um a better way of understanding
perception um and sense making is to
treat the uh to treat the problem as an
active problem of construction and the
active nature will become even more
apparent um as we get uh deeper into the
notion of active inference so this view
um I sort of mentioned 20th century um
sort of outside in perspectives but in
fact they were predated but by um this
inside out uh perspective by uh people
like Herman V hel Holz and you could
argue right the way back through can to
Plato but beautifully summarized here by
helz um as follows objects are always
imagined as being being present in the
fal division as would have to be there
in order to produce the same impression
on the nervous mechanism so again he's
referring to this notion of imagining
something on the inside and then
predicting what you would see and then
using what you're actually seeing to
update revise your hypothesis U until
you've got a good account of what's
going on and he referred to this um in
terms of um unconscious inference or or
a perceptual inference very closely
related to the Notions of Richard
Gregory in um psychology um who saw
perception as hypothesis testing again
emphasizing emphasizing an inactive
aspect um to um to our perception sort
of visually palpating the visual scene
with our eyes to gather the right kind
of evidence to test the hypothesis that
this particular um set of visual inputs
U was caused by this or that and these
ideas are been taken up in machine
learning um and artificial intelligence
research to great effect um for example
people uh like Jeffrey Hinton and Peter
Diane actually built a helmz machine um
as a a mathematical metaphor image of
the basing brain uh borrowing explicitly
from um basian statistics and the work
of Richard fan uh which is where the
free energy comes from so uh Fineman um
if you like
solved the problem of evaluating that
marginal likelihood or model evidence um
which is an intractable Problem by
converting it into an optimization
Problem by producing a bound upon uh the
log marginal likelihood or that self
information that we're talking about
earlier on um in the context of um QED
or Quantum electrod Dynamics so putting
these two together they invented the
helm HS machine um which is formally
almost exactly what we would predict
from the point of view of this physics
understanding of sense making um and we
want to now extend the story to include
action so let's come back to this notion
Helm's notion of Impressions on the
nervous mechanism so if that Bas in
interpretation of
self-organization under a given
attracting set that possesses a mark of
blanket what would that mean or how
could one describe sense making on the
inside on the internal States well it
would look as
if me on the inside I am in receipt of
these sensory Impressions on my sensory
epithelia my sensory Veil say my retina
um or my skin or my um my hearing
apparatus and they would present
themselves as Shadows um sparsely
sampled Impressions upon my sensory Veil
my the sensory sector of my Markoff
blanket and it would look as if my
internal Dynamics would trying to uh
predict or explain what caused those um
um those sensory Impressions um so how
could we think of that in terms of the
internal Dynamics well we already know
how uh how to describe the internal
Dynamics say my brain Dynamics my
neuronal Dynamics because it must be an
instance of one of these um fundamental
flow equations um so I'm going to make a
couple of moves here what I'm going to
say is if I can read my internal States
as parameterizing some variational or
probabilistic representation or beliefs
a probability distribution uh about the
external States then I can interpret
this um um
fundamental gradient flow which I've now
expressed not in terms of the log
probabilities but in terms of the the
free energies that stand in for the the
self information or the uh log um the
log values um I can now Express this in
a way that somebody in engineering would
would immediately recognize and it would
imagine also people and say perceptual
control theory would immediately
recognize the particular form here I've
written down as a calman filter um or a
simple form of um um basian filtering um
where the solenoidal part would be read
as the prediction so imagine that the
internal States me now stood in for some
expected states of the
world so that the me was now an
expectation of some say a gausian
probability distribution which means
that if I had some expectation about the
state of the world I could predict the
rate of change of the state of the world
now I don't know whether that's true or
not but I can now use the gradient Flow
Part the nons solenoidal or the
dissipated part of the gradient flow um
I can now interpret these gradients of
free energy in terms of a prediction
error and I can use that prediction
error to update my prediction to give me
a um the best guess about what's going
on out there in terms of the external
States so let me make that try and make
that um uh even more intuitive um and
just asked well what is this prediction
error well I've just said mathematically
it's just the gradients of the um the
VAR variation free energy or the
surprise or the self-information um but
intuitively what is it well imagine I
had this sensory impression on my eyes
on my retina and I had an internal brain
state that stood in for a belief that
this particular set of sensory
Impressions was caused by a howling dog
now I've had a generative model that
could generate what I would see if this
hypothesis or expectation was correct I
can then compare the ensuing prediction
with the actual sensory Impressions to
produce a prediction error and then what
this equation is saying is I'm using
that prediction error to drive changes
in my internal States my neuronal
activity say in order to eliminate the
prediction to destroy the free energy
gradient
to attenuate and resolve the prediction
error until I have found the best
explanation for this particular uh
pattern in terms of the prediction hence
predicted coding um now notice here that
this is just describing
self-organization of internal States in
relation to external States and um
communicated via sensory States in terms
of minimizing prediction error you'll
never actually know what caused your
sensation so in this particular example
it was actually a dog as sorry a cat
casting the shadow uh that looked very
look much like a dog but it doesn't
matter if I don't know all I need to do
is to keep my prediction errors low as
long as I live and then job done so
that's a very sort of parsimonious and I
find a nice way of just describing the
imperatives to sense making uh um and
action um in the sense we can forget
about the physics and just reduce it all
now to prediction error uh and you know
again for those people in perceptual
control theory this this should uh be a
story um well uh rehearsed um
so what about this sort of action
perception cycle well there are two ways
I can minimize prediction
error I can either change my mind
literally by changing my neural activity
to change the predictions of my sensory
input and make them closer to the
sensations to resolve the prediction
error in the that we've just described
but there's another way I can do that I
can actively resample my sensorium to
make my Sensations more like my
predictions and this would be action
changing Sensations to make them more
like predictions as opposed to
perception uh namely changing
predictions to make them more like
Sensations so humanistically what this
means is that we would expect to see
action fulfilling the prophecies or the
predictions afforded by perception um in
a very very simple way and just to
illustrate the Simplicity now going to
um go um sort of talk explicitly about
predictive coding uh and particularly
hierarch predictive coding of the sort
that people currently in the
neurosciences think is a nice way to
think about message passing and Dynamics
amongst different neural populations um
in the brain um so um what I've done
here is U draw a schematic of the visual
system um in its entirety so starting
off say with visual signals from the eye
reporting visual input they come into a
a nucleus subcortical nucleus called the
lateral geniculate uh nucleus um and
these visual inputs are then um in
receipt of top- down predictions and
the difference then is scored by a
prediction error that then is sent to
drive or update beliefs expectations
represented by units encoding what is
being being predicted to try and
eliminate this first order prediction
error in a hierarchical context though
we can just um repeat this process these
are now um first order predictions that
themselves are being predicted by second
order predictions that are you used to
compare with the first order predictions
to produce a second order prediction
error that then is used to drive these
higher order predictions and then so on
recursively to any uh hierarchal level
desired so that would be a picture of
hierarchal predictive coding or
hierarchal message passing or basing
belief updating all all words for the
same thing that will be consistent with
this physics view of
self-organization what about the action
well let's consider another another kind
of input the kind of input that um in
neurobiology would call proceptive input
this basically just reports the state of
my actuators the state of my motor plant
might say my muscles um uh and this
would come in say to the pontin nuclei
in the brain and it could be in receip
of top down predictions about um where I
feel my eyes pointing um and I could use
the ensuing prediction error to revise
my beliefs about where I'm looking
but there's a much simpler way of
resolving these proceptive prediction
errors I can actually just return them
to the external world and cause them to
contract my muscles until they're
reporting exactly what I predicted and
of course what I've just described is
this a classical reflex arc um sometimes
described um in the 1980s and 90s in
terms of the equilibrium point
hypothesis the notion now is that my
predictions are now Furnishing set
points that are reflexively realized in
the periphery by using the prediction
erors to destroy themselves or the the
implicit free energy gradients simply by
acting upon the external States this
instance the muscles so that I move my
eyes so I get a different kind of
information um now notice here this is
very much sort of a Clos Loop thing um
but it is deeply informed by the
predictions that are gathering evidence
from all different modalities so these
predictions are realized in a relatively
close form um setting but the
predictions in and of themselves are U
inherit from some very deep hierarchical
um sense making if you like under this
predictive coding view so that's the
that's the basic story I just want to um
um end now with with a little bit more
of a technical Nuance on this free
energy um and a conceptual proposition
um that would differentiate between the
kind of reflexive behavior that I've
just described and the sorts of behavior
that you would um study in
Psychology your decision- making under
and certainty planning to do this um
versus that um and just to sort of set
the scene um I've just Prov another
schematic here that summarizes the the
generic computational architecture that
underwrites this action perception cycle
so the idea is got our Markoff blanket
our internal States and our external
States we have the sensory sector here
providing the inputs that enable the um
the neuronal Dynamics that are
performing gradient flows on the um on
the variational free energy uh that look
as if they are optimizing beliefs
maximizing the um the um
the quality of representations or
beliefs about the causes of these ex
sensory States the external States here
to form um a expectations about states
of Affairs out there Beyond sensory um
beyond my markof blanket and then these
beliefs are used to generate uh
particular predictions specifically of
um my motor plant or my apprpriate the
the appar that I used to act upon the
world um um uh and we can read these in
terms of proception prediction eras that
then drive action that changes external
States then Supply New sensory States
and so we have our action perception
cycle now characterized or described in
terms of perceptual inference and the
ensuing action selection that is then
driven by the predictions of what the
motor plant um should um should be
registering or reporting um via Pro
perception you can get quite a long way
with this um with this construct um in
terms of producing btic behavior um this
is one of my favorite examples um
illustrates a few subtle points first of
all um sometimes the structure that you
ascribe to the world actually comes from
your own head even though you think you
are trying to just um guess the causes
of your own Sensations um under this
view or under this description um so
what we've done here is equip a a
synthetic agent with a generative model
in which the agent thinks that there's
some autonomous Dynamics um in this
instance a heteroclinic cycle that comes
from a a lot voltera um um um attractor
um that just C Ates with the
heteroclinic orbit here um and the
generative model is configured such that
the agent thinks that this abstract
movement maps to movement in some
extrapersonal ukian space and it's
pulling an invisible string uh spring my
apologies um that is connected to her
finger so she expects to see and feel a
finger being pulled around in this iant
orbit um and of course those
expectations now become descending
predictions of what she expects to feel
and what she expects to see but because
the reflexes of fulfilling the
predictions about what she expects to
feel her arm will actually or finger
will actually move thereby generating
the visual Impressions that she
predicted and satisfying those
predictions and what that looks like
from the outside is that the agent is
doing a very ele mental kind of
handwriting generating the sensations
that were predicted in both the prop
perceptive and the uh the visual domain
so just to summarize that we have these
top- down predictions in the proceptive
domain generating action uh and what
could be called corer discharge um um
generating visual predictions that are
then fulfilled by self authoring um the
causes of Sensations through actually
acting and generating what I expected to
see um one nice thing about this is we
can actually suppress the proceptive
prediction errors so there's no
information that this agent um has
available to it um that would suggest
that she or it is actually moving um
which would be a little bit like um
seeing stuff that's caused by somebody
else and then uh and by implementing
this um this adjustment we can now um
simulate action observation observing
somebody else act uh uh and compare it
to the simulated neurodynamics during
action itself but from the point of view
of the agent very little has changed
she's still got all the Machinery to
predict this kind of visual input um so
can use exactly the same um predictive
generative model generating the
predictions the same neuronal Dynamics
to actually explain the visual input and
indeed if one look looks at the activity
um of the simulated neuronal responses
one can reproduce things you find in
your B like Place field activity but
crucially the same pattern of selective
responses are listed during action and
the observation of another performing
the same action so that's uh that
particular illustration which I repeat
is is is not um unbi mtic um rests upon
the mark of blanket structure that I
described before um here detailed in
terms of the dependences what I want to
do now is just make one very small Moon
that could have a profound effect on the
way that one might describe um uh
deliberative Behavior what I'm going to
do is I'm going to remove the influence
of the active states on the internal
States my motivation for doing this is
that if things get bigger and bigger and
bigger and bigger at some point the
internal States will lose the direct
connection from the active States um and
so I'm going to remove that and that has
a very interesting
consequence it means that from the point
of view of the internal States the
active States now become a vicarious
cause of the sensory
states which means that it look as if
the brain is now encoding the internal
states are encoding the active States as
if there's a distinction between my
physical realized actions that I can
only infer through the sensy
consequences of actions I've just
cartooned the fundamental distinction
there from the point of view of this
basing mechanics or interpretation of
internal Dynamics in um um in terms of
this self- evidencing or basy mechanics
or gradient flow on the log model
evidence
um um I'm drawing a distinction between
these um the behavior of large particles
where the active States um no longer
have direct access to the internal
States um and I've drawn that in terms
of the you know the presumed beliefs of
simple things like cells where they
don't have to represent their own action
they you know the action is directly
informing and infl ing the internal
Dynamics uh in contradistinction things
like you and me um May well be better
described as having beliefs about our
own action and that's crucial and I mean
basic beliefs not propositional beliefs
here um and that's crucial because that
takes us into a different world it takes
us into a world um of planning and
inference where now because I've got
effectively beliefs about what I am
doing I now have to in defer what am I
doing if I'm making an inference I have
to have prior beliefs about um what the
kinds of things that I do and the
argument here is well what kind of
things do I do well I'm a free energy
minimizing thing therefore I must uh
more I will more likely commit to those
actions that minimize the free energy I
would expect consequent upon that action
and mathematically that leads to uh this
is what the the last slide now um a
really interesting um
decomposition of um the terms that
constitute these if you like generalized
prediction errors um or the free energy
bound on on theong evidence so forgive
the equations but the reason I put them
up is I I just want to see what happens
to various
interpretations of this um free energy
functional or function of um sensory
states and active States um when we move
into the future when we now um appeal to
the free energy as a way of evaluating
the likelihood that I will act in this
way or or that way um so what I've done
here is is write out the full expression
for the variational free energy um and
I've written it in two different ways
this is the kind of expression that
somebody from statistics would be
comfortable with and they would read
this as complexity um minus accuracy
where the accuracy is just a log
probability of some sensory States given
my belief about their causes the the
external States here the complexity is
interesting it's effectively um a
Divergence um technically a kale
Divergence but can be read just as a
difference between two kinds of
probabalistic beliefs namely um the um
what I believe um my um beliefs about
states of the world um uh given my
exposure um and the sensory information
namely my posterior beliefs after seeing
some uh data under some action um and
the PRI beliefs so it's it's it really
scores the degree to which I change my
mind in receipt of my sensory
Impressions um it's the amount of
Information Gain um or the cost I have
to play pay in in order to um move my PR
beliefs my posterior beliefs as a result
of this updating process driven by these
prediction
errors if you're in machine learning um
you would rearrange these terms um so
that you would separate the log evidence
um that we've been talking about um um
um from another K Divergence between my
approximate posterior beliefs that come
from the free energy and the exact
posterior beliefs about external States
given the sensory States um so this mean
because this can be never be less than
zero this free energy is often called an
Evidence bound um in machine learning um
sometimes with the acronym elbow because
use a negative free energy e lbo and
evidence lower bound the reason I take
you through that is that if I now say
well let's take these quantities and ask
what would they look like in the future
before I've actually got any Sensations
so now let's take um the probability
distribution over the sensations given
I'm acting in this way and use them to
take the average of these quantities and
what happens is they the complexity
becomes risk the accuracy or the
inaccuracy becomes ambiguity and the
Divergence and the log evidences become
intrinsic and extrinsic value
respectively so what are these
quantities what would they look like how
could one inter these well if we just
ignore the prior preferences the
attracting States the uh the log
evidence for a moment and assume that I
am equally attracted to all states of
Affairs what am I left with I'm left
with something called intrinsic value in
robotics it's also called intrinsic
motivation um in the visual search
literature it's called Bas in Surprise
um what is it it's very simple it's just
the degree to which I Chang my mind mind
about the external States given my
sensory observations under this action
in relation to the same beliefs before
without seeing the sensory observations
so this basically scores the information
gain or the reduction of uncertainty
about the external States it's um if you
like the imperative for expiration it is
sometimes know as a an EP scoring the
epistemic affordance of acting in this
way as opposed to acting in that way um
where the epistemic affordance just
reflects the amount of information that
I will gain if I do this as opposed to
that um from the point of view
information Theory it's just um a the
mutual information between the causes of
my sensation and the sensory
consequences the external and sensory
States
respectively let me take
um some uncertainty off the table and
see what happens let's assume that I can
see all the sensory States um and um
therefore the external States become the
sensory States and therefore there's no
ambiguity what am I left with well risk
so what is risk well it's just the
difference between what I think will
happen if I act like this and what a
priori I prefer to happen uh my
attracting external States or indeed uh
sensory States so in engineer ing this
would be known as KL uh control in
economics it could be regarded as risk
sensitive control where we where we
ignore the ambiguity and then finally if
I remove all uncertainty so there's no
uh reducible uncertainty in this
environment i' come become completely
familiar with it uh we're just left with
the um the log evidence or the extrinsic
value the expected value which we
started with which is just scoring the
expected uh um
um log probability of uh me um ending up
in my attracting set or sensory uh
subset of those attracting sets so the
final example is really just using these
equations to simulate another kind of
agent that now really thinks about the
future and acts in a way not reflexively
to minimize proceptive prediction errors
but to minimize the expected free energy
or the expected uh prediction areas in
the future by resolving UNC certainty um
and what we've done here is to simulate
a very simple agent um whose Universe
just comes along in three flavors uh all
her Sensations are caused by an upright
face a sideways face or an inverted face
the um the Restriction here is that this
agent can only see a very small part of
the visual field so has to choose very
carefully where to look and does so in a
way that responds to this epistemic
affordance this intrinsic value or um
expected Information Gain and chooses
the information Rich parts of uh of of
the image um shown here in terms of
Dynamics and what is actually sampled
and in so doing resolves uncertainty
about the three hypotheses um that best
explain this sequentially sampled um um
sensorium or visual input um showing a
progressive reduction in the uncertainty
in terms of the amazing confidence
intervals um and correctly believing now
that she is sampling from an upright
face so that can be much more succinctly
expressed um as always by helmz um and
indeed he has done that here each
Movement we make by which we alter the
appearance of objects should be thought
of as an experiment designed to test
whether we've understood correctly the
en relations of the phenomena before us
that is their existence in definite
spatial relations and so with that it
only remains for me um to thank those
people whose ideas I've been talking
about and of course to thank you for
your attention thank you very much
indeed thank you Cole thank you so much
um wonderful thank you um and um I think
we're you'll have time for plenty of
discussion and
questions um if I just start please I
can see some questions coming in the
chat but if I just start um so I think
we're going to talk some more about the
good uh regulator theorem so no need for
me to cover that off
initially but let's just maybe explore
one point and please don't um uh don't U
make the mistake of thinking that um I I
maybe all I need here is a repetition of
something that you've all already said
but when we decouple the internal States
from the active
States
um I'm trying to explore the real the
way in which this is reliant on free
energy
minimization in other words this
decoupling if I can or disconnection if
I can call it that of the um internal
from the active
in the sense is it happening because of
the principle of free energy
minimization or in the sense is it
required by that
principle that's a really excellent and
deep question and I did not cover it in
uh in this presentation because um that
the answer to that question um if
correct has only um become apparent in
the in the past few years um prior to
much of of the preparation of the
material and the story that I was
telling today um it has a clear answer
it is not a consequence of the free
energy principle uh I think generically
speaking the free energy principle is a
description of things that exist and you
know um um with a careful definition of
what you mean by existence but also a
careful definition of um the particular
um dependencies that underwrite your
definition of existence which is markup
blanket so all the free energy principle
says is if you give me a um a random
dynamical system with a particular
sparse coupling that permits the um
existence of a mark of blanket that in
turn permits me to identify something as
persisting through time um then the free
energy principle can be applied should
you want to and you may ask well why
would you want to um for fun sometimes
and literally great fund simulating
things um scientifically that that's you
know the simulation aspect is very
important um you know um being able to
actually write down the Dynamics of a
system that you think can be explained
by this kind of gen model or that kind
of G model is quite useful it also has
applications as an observation model in
phenotyping certain behaviors say in
Psychiatry um but sorry back to the
question so notice that the um the the
dynamic DCS do not inherit from the free
energy principle the free energy
principle is a description of the
Dynamics of this kind of thing so the
answer now is to your question is well
what kind of things um would um first of
all show gradient flows that um are
precisely the these Paths of least
action and in particular the kinds of
things where there's a disconnect
between or a removal of the influence of
the active states on the internal States
the the first question is things that
are not subject to lots of random
fluctuations so we're talking about big
things um things that are certainly
bigger than you know a um a Quantum
scale in which the random fluctuations
average away and the bigger they get the
few of the random fluctuations until you
actually get right you get to the um uh
the you know scale of heavenly bodies
for example where there are virtually no
random fluctuations those disputed
gradient flows disappear and we're just
left with the Divergence fre solenoidal
flow the rotation of the you know
Heavenly Bodies the you know the the
Earth around the Sun for example um but
on route as we get bigger and bigger and
bigger um there will be um a substantial
portion and an increasing portion
proportion of the internal states that
can't see the active states of the um of
the um the Markoff blanket so the the
supposition here is if you are big
enough you may be describable as
planning which says that there are small
things are unlikely to plan so you know
very in a very simple minded way you
wouldn't expect this planning as
inference to be a feature or necessary
to describe the behavior of a bacterium
or a virus but you might expect it to to
apply to a mouse and you'd certainly
expect it to apply to uh to you and me
um just because we are bigger so you so
the free energy is a method or a
description that can be applied to
things um and when applied to big things
then then then you can certainly um um
then you would be licensed to
incorporate this planning as inference
in into into the description or the
application of the method is that the
kind of wonderful very eloquent thank
you so much and um I appreciate that so
Jonathan shall we have a look at the
chat please Yes sounds good and um what
we'll do we'll take a couple of
questions from chat and then we'll go to
you David um so couple of questions in
chat so first one's from Clement Vidal
um Clement do you want to read out the
the question you put in chat or I can do
it on your behalf sure I can do it um so
how many levels of hierarchies of
predictions exist in the human brain and
do they correspond to the number of
brain
layers um
the there's a j I'm smiling because um
Chris frit and I make a joke yes there
is number it's six and then and then um
and then somebody asked why six and said
well because we said so so it's it's a
bit of a joke um but it's also not a
joke really um because again it it comes
down to very very simple um arguments um
about the size of the brain and um just
appealing in a very coar grained way to
um so re alization group what tends to
happen as you move from very lowlevel
sensory levels in these hierarchical
structures which you can read literally
as deep World models or deep generative
models where the Deep just is an
expression the fact you have this
hierarchical structure which I should
add depends upon sparsity of connections
and markup blankets so you can't Define
a hierarchy unless other than in in
terms of which connections are not there
and that is another instance of a
Markoff blanket so each layer is a blank
Markoff blanket for for all the um in a
centripetal kind of hierarchy all the
internal States um that are higher than
that so in these deep architectures what
tends to happen is you get um uh as
characteristic of the renormalization
group you get a slowing of the Dynamics
um and that and that s tells you well
how many times can you slow down
Dynamics um in a brain that only lasts
for say 5200 years uh it's usually about
six so you start off with the cognitive
moment which is about 250 milliseconds
so you keep on increasing it by an order
of magnitude say and there there's an
upper bound on the number of times you
can do that and suddenly you encroach
upon the lifetime um the time you know
the time scale over which this Mark of
blanket actually exists so probably six
is a number bound um not to be confused
with um the fact that the the so what
I'm talking about here are levels in a a
deep um world model or generative model
that are are deployed As you move
through increasingly higher levels of O
of your brain so so from V1 to V2 from
V2 to V4 which about here um about here
to V5 which would be about here yeah as
you get sort of closer to to to um retal
and uh frontal regions
um the brain itself um can be um
um can be en visited like a sort of um
like a cabbage that's covered with all
all the all the you know the neurop pill
um that contains all the um nodes that
that are connected the gray matter that
um sits like a sort of a lair which is
about 3 to 5 mm thick on top of this
cabbage where the Cabbage itself
comprises all all the connections sparse
connectivity um called the white matter
cu the they're marinated with little
fatty uh wire sheets um that that that
cortex itself has a layed structure so
you be careful when you ask somebody
like me about layers and levels because
the levels we're talking about in terms
of abst generating um uh and
contextualizing predictions so as soon
as you have this notion of hierarchal
generative model that's generating
predictions and you're saying that the
deeper levels um click over more slowly
in Universal or clock time you're
basically saying that the deeper level
provide a context for fast things at the
lower level and the fast things at the
lower level provide a context for even
faster things at the level below that um
so that that that that um notion of a
lay is really a level in a hierarchical
uh in a deep hierarchical uh um
architecture and that's very distinct
from the layers of the cortex the layers
of the cortex are really interesting
because um when one drills down on the
biological implementation of that
predictive coding scheme that I
Illustrated with predictions and
prediction error being passed around it
looks as if the prediction errors live
in the top three layers and the
predictions live in the bottom three
layers and you could actually look at
the wiring of the brain and start try to
to make sense of um the hierarchical
message passing that now has a lamin or
L specificity in the context of cortical
layers so it can be a bit confusing it's
a fascinating area to get the you know
the computation Anatomy implied by um
the sparse coupling and the you know the
predictive coding like
interpretations great thank you right
thank you um go to chance Mills next and
then to you day we so chance again do
you want me to read out your question or
or would you would you like to read it
out
yourself um I I think I'm all right with
reading it out myself thanks um so the
American Society for cybernetics
proposes you know this uh move towards
ontogenetic resilience in light of the
change of environmental factors at an
unprecedented Pace loss of biodiversity
changes in uh weather patterns
things which kind of anchor our identity
and connection to the world so my
question is this in light of the uh free
energy principle what is the Adaptive
strategy for dealing with uh such a
situation um that's you know a very
challenging question uh I'm one would be
tempted to answer that on two levels
first of all you know how um how would
you describe adaptation under the free
energy principle you could also answer
it how would you use the free energy
principle to try and ameliorate some of
the challenges that are currently facing
as in terms of um um overconnectivity
and runaway uh Dynamics a failure of
self-organization which is what would be
predicted under this the fearing
principle perhaps I'll just make that
point clear because I think it's I feel
quite passionately about that um the
everything that I have said in terms of
being able to um describe
self-organization to an attracting set
which I think from is just a description
of self- sustaining systems that is a
definition of sustainability at the
level of of um of certainly of physics
rests upon the sparsity of coupling um
it rests upon the connections that are
not there so if you go around
globalizing and increasing connectivity
you're destroying markup blankets if you
destroy markup blankets you destroy
um um self-organization you know
technically from a dynamical system
perspective you're inducing oscillated
deaths everywhere and one could argue
that that's what we what we are
potentially confronted with at the
moment in terms of overconnectivity and
a destruction of all the sparse coupling
um that preserves those delicate
structures that have self-organized them
over Millennia organize themselves o
over Millennia so if he wanted to apply
the free energy principle um to render a
particular system be it an ecosystem be
it a financial Market be it a um uh um
meterological system if you could
intervene on it um to improve its
resilience what you are looking at is a
way of uh preventing the destruction of
sparse connectivity to to preclude um uh
over connectivity uh to to to maintain
those boundaries and that segregation in
the right kind of way um which means you
know I guess ideologically um putting
more regulation in place uh it means
having very very clear geopolitical
boundaries you know Mark of blankets you
know in a um in a sustainable way um um
um finding mechanisms that would
preclude um uh breaches of Markoff
blankets um you know if I was a um an
oncologist these breaches would be
basically cancer you know cells growing
Beyond their natural boundaries because
they now become um um um poor Regulators
or or models of their local cellular
econ Niche um or you could you look at
the your Wars in Ukraine for example as
the equivalent kind of failure of a
boundary or Mark of blanket at a
geopolitical level um so that's how I
would apply the free energy um as an
academic how will you describe this I
think it speaks to something we
mentioned before which is separation
temporal scales all that I was talking
about during the presentation was
focusing on um one Temple scale which
was inferring states of the world states
of Affairs out there but exactly the
same um mechanics applies to um the
parameters of a generative model which
as a neurologist would be the brain
connectivity for example if you're
machine learning it would be the
connection strengths or the weights in
say a Transformer model um and ALS Al to
the structure of um these uh you know
these good models these these generative
models U by structure I mean you know
the number of levels in a hierarchical
structure the number of components the
um the particular structure that
um endows it with a deep or hierarchical
structure all of these things have to be
optimized in relation to the free energy
that takes you into the world of
evolution um um in the a very simple
sense that the free energy statistics is
used to do Bas in model selection but
you can also read natural selection as
Nature's way of doing Bas in model
selection selecting the right phenotype
that's a good model of that phenotypes
lived World um so you've got these
different different time scales in play
so I think adaptation of the time the
kinds of time scales that your question
Intimates would have to I think appealed
both to parametric learning um and
structure learning um um uh both of
which can be expressed as free energy
minimizing or evidence maximizing uh
processes um and you're in the face of
of a changing environment um that in in
turn speaks to interesting differences
between inference and learning where
inference is updating your um your
embodied beliefs about states of Affairs
hidden latent States in machine learning
talk um learning would be Bas in belief
updating the parameters of Your World
models and then um structure learning or
selection we'll be selecting the right
kinds of structures each one um nested
within uh the other with a separation of
time scales so you know for example I
can't make sense of my sensorium um
unless I've learned the right kinds of
contingencies of um um and I can't learn
the right kinds of contingencies Say ne
during neurod development unless I got
the right brain structure so every one
of these scales depends upon the you
know all the other ones and of course
that uh that also holds in reverse that
you know my brain wouldn't ex exist
unless I had you know a structure and of
course I wouldn't have the wiring uh in
order in order to do the message passing
to make to do perception uh so all of
these different scales depend uh depend
upon depend upon each other is that the
kind of answer you were looking for
or yes thank thank you very much
Professor David we'll go to you next and
after David we'll go to Trevor
Hilda okay uh well thank you uh very
much for elucidating and giving me a far
better feel for perception information
processing and uh moving towards action
I don't want to pretend to have
understood and digested everything that
uh you've said
um completely uh Professor kisten what
I'm interested in is how far you see
this form of analysis of moving towards
kind of dissolving
the uh
sensation uh body problem the hard
problem the issue of qualia or um raw
field is information um prior
to sensation is sensation a concept we
have no need of or does it emerge out of
processing our processing um so to speak
I I just wondered if you could sort of
help me around this area or whether
philosophically you regarded it as a non
question no I I'm not allowed to regard
it as a non- question I have too many
philosophy friends but because I don't
do philosophy it's it's not a question I
can help you with but I can get I can
point you to the kinds of answers on the
literature where people are really
focusing on this um uh but it is a
philosophical question um from my point
of view um
you the question really reduces to what
what kinds specifically what structures
um
um specifically of the gened models
would be necessary in order for um some
artifact natural or otherwise to be
sentient in the way that you're you're
you're implying yeah um and you know
what most people end up um um end up
with is a number of different arguments
you can take the agency argument um
which I quite like you know to be uh to
be um sentient is to be an agent so it's
me actually Gathering my data and
possibly experiencing my data or or not
but before I can experience it I I have
to be me and therefore I have to be an
agent so immediately you're talking
about um um how would you define agency
in you know as a physicist um and if you
defined agency of A non-trivial Sort as
the kind that inherits from um the uh
representing the consequences of my own
action that tells you a number of things
immediately it tells you that certain
things possibly viruses cannot be
sentient in the way that an agent could
be it also tells you that um things that
have sentients if they are agents must
have a generative model of the future um
in the sense that in order for me to
predict the consequences of my action to
plan I have to have a ger a model of the
future in the sense that the
consequences not yet occurred which
means there's a certain temporal
thickness to these World models that you
possibly wouldn't find in a virus or a
thermostat but you might find in me um
so that might be one bright line between
the kinds of things that can be sentent
and well to have an agentic S sentience
um and then you move on to um other
perspectives um some perspectives
emphasize as you mentioned the body so
I'm thinking about the work with people
like Anil Seth here and Lisa Feldman
Barrett they they say that well to be to
have minimal selfhood is just the
hypothesis that the best explanation for
this Myriad of Sensations from my eyes
and my body my skin um the best
explanation for it is I am an embodied
being and I am me and all of this um is
the best explanation for what's going on
so now selfhood itself becomes another
um becomes another um hypothesis um
which you have to ask why would you have
that hypothesis well one advantage of
having that hypothesis once you realize
I am me um is you can now exert mental
action over um which things you attend
to that's quite a long story here but
I'm just slipping in the key words that
that some people think that it's not any
agency that makes you sentent it's a
particular kind of agency that's on the
inside it's basically attending to
different sectors of your Markoff
blankets um that basically allows you to
select what
information you are going to use to do
your updating about myself and my plans
so there are people um usually German
philosophers who would focus on on
mental action as necessary for uh for
that kind kind of sentience and and and
minimal selfhood and then you get into
um even even more um contentious issues
about um um self-awareness and having
models of me in different states of mind
you know is the hypothesis that I am a
person and I am anxious um is that part
of my generative model and what would
that look like in terms of James Langan
um sort of formulations of your of of
emotions and their bodily Expressions so
really fascinating answers a question uh
and lots of fascinating answers but but
there are lots of them so I think you
just have to take your pick from from
your favorite philosopher I think that's
yeah so will turning an artificially
intelligent system off ever be morally
equivalent to Knocking somebody
out yeah um if you if you could engineer
such such a um a sentent yes I think so
I mean that's a little bit um I don't
like knocking people out because that's
usually has more as in a psychiatrist
neurologist this is you shouldn't really
do that if you can avoid it but certain
like putting some to sleep or unitizing
them yeah yeah it would be it would be
very much like that the argument now is
will you ever get um
um a btic intelligence um you know in an
artifact I don't see why not provided
that artifact is embodied so that you
know you give it the opportunity to
learn oh I am embodied and I am a thing
um and I can plan um and yes in
principle yeah it would it would be like
switching you you switching you off when
you went to sleep for example
you thank
you um Trevor do you want to go next and
then after
treasure thank you thanks very much
thank thanks Professor Frist um I wonder
if you could comment on the thousand
brains theory about how the neocortex
works
yes I can yeah so Jeff um
um um Hawkins the inventure of the pine
Palm P pilot for those of you who can
remember the Palm Pilot uh so um there
are lots of similarities but some key
differences between the kind of um
canonical micro circuits that that are
um on offer to if you like um explain
one instance of predictive coding the
similarities um inherit from sort of a a
common interest in trying to get a btic
formulation of um sense making and
action so in fact Jeff Hawkins hosted uh
a meeting it must be 30 years ago now
when I was a young man where you know we
started talking about these things
shortly afterwards he worked with a
gentleman called diip George who's still
doing quite um exciting work I think at
newor together they came up with
something called the hierarchical
temporal model the HTM and that shares
exactly the same fundamental
characteristics that we're talking about
before in terms of the um the separation
of temporal scales As you move deeper
and deeper into generative models so
there's a you there's a shared
commitment um not just to generative
modeling as a view a constructive view
of sense making and and action and
pneumonics um uh but that also extends
into the very very specific
architectures that speak to a separation
of Temple skills um which was celebrated
in Jeff's early work the Thousand brains
one um does you know it's gone off in
its own particular direction and I think
that the know the connection here would
be more like um a mixture of experts
perspective on generative models so I
think a very plausible uh notion that um
you could have um a whole bunch of
generative models all competing to
explain the lowest level of a sensory
hierarchy um and each one will be fit
for purpose for a different context and
one way that they can if you like
resolve uh infer the particular context
in which they're operating is to compete
to see who can explain this sensory
input the most so in statistics this is
called Bas in model averaging uh where
you wait the predictions of each model
in proportion to the free energy or the
evidence log evidence sorry the evidence
for each model I think what Jeff has in
mind from my point of view would be
there you know there are millions of
these little mixtures of experts that
are all competing so I think it fits
very comfortably with the overall fre
energy principle probably less
comfortably with um predictive coding of
the of with specific architectures that
will be informed by
neurobiology um you know the Thousand
brains formulation is is
not is not quite um doesn't have quite
same commitments as the normal canonical
microcircuit formulation of predictive
coding uh and the empirical evidence
speaks to the canonical microcircuit
formulation just because the chical
microcircuit formulation was designed to
account for the empirical evidence
whereas Jeff didn't have to worry about
that because he he you know he's just
trying to find the right architectures
but a lot of shared commitments some
differences some nuances and I I'd be
interested to see what it comes up with
in the next 10 years it's great thank
you very much
you um we'll go to Margaret Heath next
Margaret I see you've got a couple of
questions in there so if you want to
cover both of those that'll be brilliant
thanks hello yes thank you Professor
fiston um thank you for all your work
it's really it's it's yummy um I have a
question that is on on two levels really
um the one is uh to do you've discussed
in other lectures um this notion of
temporal death and counteract short
breath and typically theories of the
imaginary or the imagination think of
this as as disconnected from sensory
information or the external and
something that happens internal to the
organism curiously I'm quite interested
in Andy's extended mind stuff and the
distribut cognition Collective cognition
where you'd have ensembles of Agents
doing stuff like this so that would
change the formulations a little I was
wondering if you could talk to us about
those sorts of ideas yeah I mean by
Coincidence of course the you know the
notion of counterfactual breadth um that
is if you like another dimension to the
temporal depth um came from a Neil Seth
and Neil Seth has an office next to Andy
as um you know Andy clar being the
author of the extended mind and and
designer environment so I think there's
a lot uh you
know they they clearly have their own
views of things but there's also a lot
of synergy between between the two you
know Anil focusing more recently on
embodiment and being a beast machine
where whereas um and is I think you know
generalizes the importance of
situatedness and and embodiment um um so
um so I think there's a very a very
close connection between those
perspectives and you can trace the
legacy of these ideas I'm sure you have
done you know from you know historical
writings that um have emerged in terms
of people like Andy Clark and Neil Seth
and and the like in terms of the you
know um the IM the counterfactual
breadth being divorced from the
sensorium I think that must be right in
this because there's no full divorces if
you allow for this vicarious sparse
connectivity that just is the the
message passing or the belief updating
in a hierarch architecture we're talking
about but um I think sort of just common
sensical yes if you are planning what to
do and you're planning in the future
you're planning a roll out uh a
trajectory a path into the future
clearly there are no um observable
outcomes from the future so it is purely
counterfactual and um as soon as you
entertain more than one path into the
future you don't have to I mean
thermostat doesn't you it just considers
one little tiny trajectory into the
future but if if we're now um you know
in the planning as inference kind of um
um active influence or predictive
processing then then you're going to
have more than one path you're going to
evaluate that and of course the the
number of paths that you evaluate is
exactly the counterfactual depth that
Anil um was referring to and it also
introduces interesting semantics which
philosophers um like which of course
once you've got um more than one
path to select from you induce a problem
of selection now as a mathematician
that's fine that's Bas in model
selection I just I just select the one
with the greatest evidence or the the
least expected free energy um but of
course if you're a philosopher you've
now got the notion of free will because
you've got the act of selecting amongst
the
counterfactuals uh or Not Free Will
depending upon uh if it's prescribed
byy yeah yeah so yeah I think um yeah I
think yes it has to be imaginal in the
sense that it is imagining a future and
you can de articulate that under
simulation theory for example um um and
in that sense it is divorced from the s
from the sensory input but of course it
is underwritten by you you by the
sensory input because your your paths do
depend upon where am I at the moment and
that is conditioned upon sense making um
so
yes and soorry just to um then make the
link to if you think about Levan's itive
cognition work all right so and the mark
of blankets and and then I listened to a
really fascinating Chris Fields with you
uh on Psy philosophy Babble I think it
was where we spoke about um that
boundary condition the information
processing at on the boundary and then
the distinction between two Mark of
blankets and how to unpack that when are
there one mark of blanket and when do
you have to compute them as separate
entities and with separate
agency yeah you're bringing in a whole
other fascinating World here you people
like Mike L and Chris Fields uh um and
you know they would talk about things
like distributed cognition and basil
cognition and ascribing the more
Elemental kind of active infant I was
describing ascribing them to sort of
even molecules or at least macro
molecules and cells asking questions
about the emergence of multi cellular
organizations and the intracellular
signaling and would this be described as
well it certainly would and could be
described as active inference and of
course once you do that you can use the
the teeology that you get from cognition
and hence distrib cognition um so I I
very much encourage that and um and
encourage um Chris fields in his Mantra
that you know in reality there should be
no difference between um physics and
psychology um and biology and philosophy
they're all the same thing and we should
all be using the same words quite merily
and an interchangeable way and I would
fully subscribe to that um the just one
interesting example of that which um I I
always like to reiterate um is you know
once you understand that you or once you
allow yourself to um with W with gay
abandon use cognitive terms to describe
the behavior of cells either maintaining
or destroying their markof blankets you
can now as Mike does and has done uh
talk about cancer as a delusion you know
a false inference and you can start to
sort of think you know think in a way
which I think is quite an expressive and
interesting way to think about the know
physical phenomena at the cellular or
the B the molecular level in terms of
this kind of um um um you know not
ascribing intentions to to cancer but
but there certainly the same kind of
collective or um situated cognition that
societies of PE of things like you and
me uh you might might express it also
the two final points here of course you
know there isn't just one mark of
blanket there are probably not an
infinite number but certainly almost
uncountable because of all the common
toric so any sparsely coupled system you
can draw a markup blankets everywhere um
and of course you can have markup
blankets of markup blankets so you
really usually have to identify the
markof blanket of interest and that
defines you as a psychologist or
molecular biologist or sociologist or
ethologist or whatever uh that just you
that's your scale of markof blanket and
that kind of markof blanket is what you
like to uh to talk about um so you know
as we intimated before just having a
deep generative model or generative
model means there are multiple Markoff
blankets in the brain and I mentioned
that because Chris more recent
has coming back to to David's question
he more recently um um uh tried to
understand what you the locus of
sentience in terms of Consciousness as
um in terms of an inner screen um and or
and the notion of irreducible Markoff
blanket so there may be one Markoff
blanket right in the middle of our
brains in the pineal gland that cannot
because of its lack of sparcity U
contain any more Mark of blankets within
it and that has some special
characteristics that uh Chris argues
might might U you know might be
associated with Consciousness you
introduced Fields there in terms of um
his take on Mark of blankets his take is
um beautiful and Abstract um uh and
comes from Quantum information Theory
where effectively he replaces a markof
blanket with a holographic screen I
think that you know that's that's what
you were you were referring to which is
a wonderful uh move uh sometimes a
little bit beyond me because I've
forgotten all my quantum physics but it
is it is an interesting move to make um
to think about the relationship between
um communication and exchange between
the internal and the external bulk um
via a holographic screen because the
holographic principal tells you all the
stuff on the inside all the information
on the inside bulk has to be on the
surface on the blanket on the
holographic screen which basically means
that everything I need to know or that
is knowable about you is on your Markoff
blanket it's just how we exchange and
that means I will never quite know
what's going on inside your head and can
never know by definition so that has
some interesting uh consequence I think
for it's just delightful isn't it thank
you thank thank you um we'll go to
Harris nei2 next and then Dave I see you
put a number of comments in Dave so
we'll then go to you after after
Harris so
Harris you could summarize the question
you put in chat that would be great
thank you yes great talk and really
insightful answers uh thank you and here
is my question uh scribes in ancient
times were tasked with copying text by
hand and it was a rather laborious and
timec consuming process uh those scripes
aim to minimize the effort expended in
the copy process much like physical and
biological systems they strove to
achieve the most efficient and accurate
production of the original text while
minimizing Surprise by reducing the
likelihood of introducing errors uh they
developed techniques uh such as using
templates employing standard tise
formats and even utilizing Pimon
mneumonic devices uh improve efficiency
and accuracy so Professor friston
considering the parallels between the
least action principle in physics and
the free energy principle in cognitive
science is it safe to utilize these
principles to inform our understanding
of human cognitive processes in
activities that required uh this extra
medul precision and
optimization such as the man manuscript
copying work of those
cpes yes I I I think well is it safe to
apply it um that's a loaded question but
a very nice question I think yes I think
it would be perfectly viable to apply
that and I think it's very good of you
to actually introduce a notion of a you
know a principle of leased action uh
because that's just what the free energy
principle is it's nothing more than a
principle of leased action so you can
articulate it using a path intrical
formulation literally as the um
understanding both action and perception
as evincing or just pursuing Paths of
least action which is as you are
intimating um Paths of Maximum
efficiency Paths of minimum error Paths
of Maximum replic
replicability Paths of Maximum uh and
and sustainable um um and resilient uh
reliability um that that you know if you
if if something was able to um persist
and exist on its own attractor its own
um in its own preferred States very very
precisely you you would get exactly the
behavior of your scribes so I imagine
they had a very comfortable and relaxed
life with this very very specific model
of what they do and they did it
perfectly um and you know and in that
sense they I think would be an example
of something that would easily be
described in terms of a path of least
action um and as such um you would be
fair to apply the free energy principle
to you know to to that to to that kind
of behavior i g I guess what you'd have
to ask though um is well if we are just
trying to minimize prediction errors you
know would you would your scribes ever
become creative would they become poets
would they start to experiment with
different artistic Scrolls um uh and
then one gets into the interesting
questions well where does that kind of
information seeking come from and then
of course the answer from the point of
view of the free energy principle it's
only when you get big enough that you
now have the opportunity to think about
the consequences of your action and then
that Curiosity that epistemic aordance
that expected Information Gain starts to
come into play so again you might think
that scribes that committed their entire
lives just to copying
manuscripts were um were were U you know
were not um probably got quite bored I
assume they had quite big brains so so
they probably wanted to to automate that
and do something that sat in their
curiosity uh because you can get a
machine to do that because the machine
doesn't plan in the it's not it doesn't
have that epistemic explorative um
capacity that that a machine does or you
know uh um um a calculator would and I
mean calculator in in the original sense
of you know um people actually do
calculations at the beginning of the
Industrial Revolution so a very
interesting question is that is that
what you meant yes yes thank you so much
great answer thank
you thank you thank you after David
we'll then go to arand van campen and
then Richard Barry so David do you
wantan to go next Dave Douglas me me
great thanks okay welcome Carl okay I've
been in many of your presentations at
active inference Institute now today
you've met mention the richness of the
Markov blanket Concept in various
contexts now we know paper of yours from
a few years ago I'm sorry I forget the
title you mention that the blanket
around an informational regime within uh
a living tissue particularly
neurological tissue might or might not
coincide with cell membranes or tissue
boundaries do you have any further
thoughts you can share with us about
that there are some people on on this
side of the pond who would be very
pleased to um reflect on your thinking
about how one
differentiates um a psychological
process from the people in which that
process embeds itself or a a meme from
the various uh brain tissues that the
meme uh embeds itself
uh we we're updating the U work of Doc
Professor Gordon pasque who I think
addressed some of these same questions
in a very concise or incisive way and I
think simplifies things by m simplifies
the work to be done by slightly
multiplying the number of conceptual
tools to be
used can can can you expand upon that
last last sentence
well I should repeat the the the the the
the
gist
um
the when we talk the the there's
traditionally go going back to beralan
there are there's been a lot of many
many times people have pointed out that
a lower or in your terms a faster level
of activity may be controlled or steered
or motivated by a higher level or a
slower level of control so you have this
res this
asymmetric Mutual influence and control
and
communication Duality parel okay now
usually the Assumption has been that
there's a single way to perform that
kind of
analysis in fact that it's just a simple
if you have multiple levels that if you
have two more than two levels to deal
with there is necessarily a strong or
weak ordering among levels of control
okay there's the word of God there's the
traditions of men there's your physi
there's your work as a farmer and
there's your physiological needs and
there's a strict hierarch or One A
controls B controls C controls D and
that that individuation occurs in one
and only one way it's just control
control is control presupposition is
presupposition now Gordon P working in
the 50s 60s and 70s along with some some
of our colleagues still around still
active in
cybernetics discovered that well in the
realm of teaching of of teaching and
learning it's much simpler to say no
wait a minute don't try to conflate all
control relations into a single con
there are after all psychological
processes and there are mechanical or
physiological
processes the physiological processes
are
spatiotemporally distinguished M
machines you can look at the boundaries
they have a boundary in uh in space they
have origins in time but the phys the
psy and the psychological processes also
have boundedness but it's not that same
kind of boundedness where is Beethoven's
Symphony I want to know where the
exactly the spot temporal boundaries of
that are it's it's a category here so
Pas just says look there's
individuation into
Minds psychological entities
memes and there's also individuation
into
spatiotemporally bounded things
regions it is the
case that mental entities control and
listen to other mental entities it's the
case in um I'll say the organization of
a thunderstorm perhaps or or you know
dirty water is a better example
turbulent dirty water that there's
there's control of large uh small the
the possibilities of small entities by
large entities but the large entities
are also dragged around by the small
entities so you have that control and it
Al also the case more importantly
perhaps that sometimes a mental entity
say a meme in the in the classic sense
controls the the the um the web browsing
activities of a number of individuals
and at that point the psychologically
differentiated
individuals acting among themselves
control and are influenced
by physical entities the fact that your
electricity went out today he knocks out
an entire class of mechanical entities
the computers aren't working
and I know that in in one of your papers
explaining the physiology of uh
predictive processing and active
inference you at the end of one of the
sections in about one sentence say it's
not clear that the boundaries of
the that the functional
processes always coincide with the
boundaries between cells or between
tissues that's the point where my ears
stuck out and I said I remember Gordon
pasque telling me about that in
1975 here's Carl frisen please tell us
more about that is there more than one
kind of individuation either
instrumentally in sense in the sense
that oh I feel like dividing the world
up in this way or I can divide it up
that way or I can divide it up both ways
and then see how they fit together or
maybe cells and memes and songs and
cultures and legal traditions and
biological species individuate
themselves in various ways Dave I think
I think you posed the question great
Carl you want to respond yeah well there
a lot to respond to that was
Illuminating I didn't know about that
work but it all sounds um very sensible
from my point of view uh and the kind of
work that I should know about um so in
brief uh you know the way that you were
talking about the separation temporal
scales and the circular causality I
understand that from um the work of say
hman hen and you know in terms of you
know the the the slaving principle and
your top down and bottom up causation
that and I think that that that is that
that view is nicely evinced with the
recursive message passing in these deep
generative models it also makes entire
sense that um you should be able to um
apply things like the pre free energy
principle to different kinds of things
whether they are memes or communication
or um
um the products of um
um products of culture for example right
down to um amoeba and single cells that
have spatial temporal poundes absolutely
you know the free energy principle is
just a principle which I mean by which I
mean it is a method it's a tool that you
can apply it to um could you apply it to
um things with you know spacious
temporal boundaries like a cell
absolutely people do that uh could you
apply it to something more abstract um
such as the passing of memes on on the
web for example absolutely people have
done that um and I think that you know
the Markoff blanket there is not really
quite so well defined spatial temporary
it's more as you would Define it in a
you know if you're a systems theorist it
would just be input output relationships
so you know in terms of systems theory
the mark of plank is nothing more than
defining the system in terms of its
inputs and out puts so you'd have to
sort of label the inputs and outputs on
on your um um on your Bluetooth or your
ethernet uh in a social web and that and
that would be the you know the way of
defining the mark the the conditional
dep sorry the sparse connectivity that
defines the Markoff blanket um and then
it wouldn't quite Define Beethoven's
Symphonies but it it would allow you to
to to then talk about the Markoff
blankets of this community or this
social group and the exchange of ideas
provided they could you know they could
be classified or Quantified in some
formal way as message passing between
Markoff blankets and you know and you
should be able to apply the freey
principle I say it's been done it's been
done in a very Elemental way um by
looking at um opulation voting Dynamics
by simulating agents passing messages on
the web but in a very simple way in
proportion or in a way that that each
agent believes in the veracity of
another P agent's belief depending on
how similar that agent is to itself um
and then you get some really interesting
polarization Dynamics through this
multi-agent active inference that I
think you could describe in terms of you
know passing memes uh and the collective
commitment to a meme I think would would
start to speak to this more abstract
mindful kind of application that that
you were intimating
yeah right thank
you um we only got a few minutes left so
i' like to squeeze in the last two
questions so Arend do you want to go
next and then we'll finish off with
Richard yes thank you Dr friston really
great to be here and see you live I I
watched you on with Lex Ritman a while
ago huh um my question would be uh I
worked with Dr F of CA who I a picture
I'm going to see here
and and he says in 1991 so my question
is would you agree with the observation
of f of CA that Global disorder social
entropy is caused by a crisis of
perception
um I think I will have to go away and
think about that
um it speaks very much doesn't it to the
earlier question about you know could
one use um
free energy principle and related uh
formulations to talk about um um
um societal uh disorder uh in terms of
communication and the way that we
perceive others um I I I think it would
be trivial of me to try and give you you
know a clever or informed answer without
thinking about this it it does uh I mean
one useful thing uh I think that could
be um brought to the table here is that
the the free energy principle is dual to
James's maximum entropy principle which
of course is you know could be cast as
what are the constraints on a particular
kind of disorder but the twist um from
the point of view of the free energy
principle is the entropy that James was
talking about was the entropy of the
measurement it was the observation and I
think read as a perception I think
there's a deep connection now between
James's Maxim enty principle which you
know for him is how does say how does a
physicist perceive by doing her
measurements um and you know almost
paradoxically saying that the best the
best kind of perception is maximizing
the entropy of the measurement
representation which for for the free
energy principle would be the um the
variance of that um Q distribution over
the external states that are be that are
being measured so I think there is some
deep connection between perception as
measurement and the and and
observation and um the natural tendency
of things to minimize their
thermodynamic free energy and maximize
their representational entropy um what
that means for the entropy and the
disorder of the of the thinging of
themselves I'll have to think
about yes I was just referring to the
work of Kenneth Bailey a social entropy
Theory uh which I've been looking at and
that's why the perception the
observation the interpretation of real
reality differs right so that is the I
think the the cause of many many
misinterpretation and many Mis actions
at this time causing this social entropy
yes yeah we don't have time but you know
it it would be really nice to talk about
sort of um some of the pathologies of
perception from the point of view of
applying the fenry principle to
psychiatric conditions like
hallucinations and delusions sensory
attenuation and what that would look
like in terms of communities talking to
each other making inferences about each
other uh some really fascinating uh
fascinating issues there yeah thank you
sir thank you thank you Richard I'll you
want to ask you do the last question and
if everybody hasn't seen it there's a
question to us all collectively from
Paul pangara but we we won't have time
to cover that so Richard you want to go
ahead uh thank you thank you Professor
fascinating to I'll try and um use pass
and and minimize my uh use of of free
energies um so
um we make decisions as a
society collectively um
we draw inference from the world and
information we are
provided um sometimes very inaccurately
um and I'll go back to the butler
inquiry and the
decision um to go to war on incorrect
inference around weapons of mass
destruction we see it daily in the
courtrooms where um 12 good citizens
will be asked to draw inference from um
evidence that they perceive has been
presented to them and make some some
pretty high-risk decisions um around
individuals and of course we get it
wrong and the post post office inquiries
is a really really good example of
collectively getting it wrong so so my
question really really straightforward
um is there a way we can manage um what
you've described in
a a more consistent way and draw
inference sorry have more confidence in
the way we draw inference um from from
the
world um I think the short answer um
you would be um you're you're not going
to find a cure but you can certainly
articulate the problem that would reveal
strategies to cure and I you and I'm
using the word cure presuming of course
you don't want to have this um this this
extremely unstable and unpleasant
situation where you just don't know
where to turn for for Reliable
information so everybody has lost
epistemic trust in everybody else with
fake news and the like and I've also
heard the argument just to generalize
that um in terms of you know young
people nowadays having so much access to
different channels of information on
social media and elsewhere that's an
incredible burden on their mental health
and I think that would be usefully
understood um In The Same Spirit you
know you know you don't know which um
you and I don't know which News Channel
to trust if we you know happen across
American news channels it's very
difficult to know you know is is this
reliable information or not from the
point of view of the free energy
principle um and applying it to um
understand what has gone wrong and how
it could be remed um it's very very
simple that you know if you if the
imperatives for a sustainable
maintenance of your manof blankets and
the implicit attracting set rests upon
minimizing
surprise and the expected surprise that
underwrites your planning is literally
uncertainty or ENT y the expected self-
invation is the entropy what that means
is we are all in the game of choosing
those actions that minimize uncertainty
and coming back to what we're talking
about before about the counterfactual we
have to choose between different actions
and if we have many many more actions
available then necessarily there's going
to be an entropy or uncertainty over
what we're going to do and that can be
incredibly that has been associated with
angst so if I if I represent that and I
have the hypothesis what state of mind
am I in and I now don't know what to do
next that is anxiety and that has direct
physiological and neuroendocrine uh
consequences so if that is true what
that means is if I've got too many
choices and I cannot trust which which
uh what actions to make sorry I cannot
trust um um the differential reliability
of various sources of information
because of this overconnectivity
um that necessarily distributes the
probability Mass over all the things I
could do that necessarily increases my
anxiety So you you're looking at the the
way that we select sources of
information for building our world
models and our beliefs as a problem of
actively selecting the right kind of
data plac you know whether this is just
in eye movements you know from moment to
moment or whether it's actually
subscribing to a particular News Channel
or social group making that that is an
action and it's an action exactly in the
service of trying to uh maximize the
expected information game that depends
upon the quality of the Precision of the
information if that job is made almost
impossible because there are so many
people shouting at me as an adolescent
um um the you I can you can see
immediately how one this would lead to a
a pernicious and irreducible uncertainty
about how to act and select the right um
the right sources of information or
points of reference or Role Models um
that will itself then produce um you
know a me a a self moral that is imbued
with anxiety and angst and just knowing
not not knowing what to do next so that
was the kind of pathology I was talking
about right at the beginning when I was
talking about overconnectivity U if you
just if it's just your teacher and your
mother and your father and your your
priest depending upon your your culture
and you in view them with an epistemic
trust then this issue goes away but that
does require a very sparse much more
familiar communal kind of uh interaction
and belief sharing and evidence
accumulation is that is that the sort of
um yeah we didn't get as far as talking
about juwes and the legal systems use of
of influence that's itself an
interesting issue
yeah yeah certainly thank you um I I
think it's one to to sort of work
through um and and take forward so
really really helpful thank
you then I think we are done Jonathan we
are we are done yes so thank you Carl
brilliant yes we brought the ship in
almost a Time thank you so much um I
think Carl you heard how many people
were referencing you from different uh
for around the place so you're certainly
leaving an impression thank you so much
uh could not ask for more thank you and
um please keep in touch thank you all
wonderful discussions thank you so much
yes thank you everyone for the questions
and just for listening and participating
thank you good night thank you thanks
Carl thanks all microphones are off but
I'm sure the houses are Rippling with
Applause thank you
right thank you
m